[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
the basic kinematics the
uh kinematics of the Hubble
law kinematics of the expanding
universe made
one assumption
which is
motivated mostly by
observation that uh the universe is
spatially
flat spatially flat means that space at
a given instant of
time is just ordinary uh ukian
three-dimensional
space but the space time itself is not
ordinary
ukian I shouldn't say ukian is not
ordinary manowski space manowski space
let's just compare the two manowski
space just to remind you is the space of
special
relativity space time of special
relativity and it has a
metric uh or a proper time element
that's given by the sum of four terms or
the difference of four terms dt^ 2
minus D x^2 and I'm going to put this in
a bracket minus D x^2 + D y^2 + D
z^2 now this is the uh the term in the
bracket is a dead giveaway of course
that space is flat it's just good old
cartisian
ordinary
uh ukian
space where the size of a line element
DX Dy DZ is just given by Pythagoras's
formula three-dimensional Pythagoras's
formula the new
element
in cosmology and now when I say the new
element in cosmology first of all I
should say the new element in the
general theory of relativity is that the
coefficients
here uh which are simply in this case
one -1 -1 minus one first of all there
are more of them there can be things
like the X d y and dydt and so forth but
the coefficients can depend on position
in
SpaceTime that means that the
coefficients are fields and basically
they are the generalization of Newton's
gravit well Newton didn't think in terms
of fields but we can think in in terms
of fields that the generalization of the
Newtonian fields of gravity the
coefficient functions which go there
now um
observationally
cosmology appears the universe that we
can see through
telescopes appears to be on the
whole I'll call it featureless of course
it has features the features of galaxies
planets Stars clusters super
clusters but that's all small potatoes
that's all small stuff on the scale SC
of billions of light
years the un uh certainly on the scale
of billions of light years on the scale
of uh several hundred million light
years the universe is very
featureless just um the same everywhere
as homogeneous is the
word
homogeneous it's isotropic it means it
looks the same in every
direction on such large scales and
this is somewhat of a slightly larger
surprise to
cosmologists incidentally the isotropy
and the
homogeneity has been with us since the
very beginning of
cosmology it the very beginning of
cosmology meaning post Hubble
cosmology uh from 1930s or 40s or
whenever
um cos mology modern cosmology started
it was always assumed that space was
homogeneous not space time but space is
homogeneous and isotropic and that was
given a name it was called the
cosmological
principle and once it's a principle it
has to be right and so
therefore it's not only a principle but
we proved it we proved it by calling it
a
principle of of course
it's of course has never been
mathematically proved or never argued
from any basic theoretical underlying
principle there is none but remarkably
the more that we look out into space the
more we see that the principle looks to
be very very accurate on the large
enough scales so isotropy and
homogeneity and one additional fact
space looks
flat space looks
flat which means that we were not so far
off by writing the X2 + the y^2 + the
z^2 but while it looks flat it also is
expanding so the picture you should have
roughly in the back of your
head uh is a flat sheet of
rubber and the flat sheet of rubber is
being stretched at a certain rate but
it's infinite it's flat now of course we
don't know the universe is really
infinite how well how well do we know
that the universe is either infinite or
flat if it's perfectly flat of course
it's got to be infinite if it goes on
and on forever if it's perfectly flat
unless there's some sort of walls out
there nobody thinks there's walls out
there um it will go on and on forever
and
ever so a flat universe is also likely
to be an infinite universe but of course
we don't really know that the universe
is either infinite or perfectly flat we
know it to the same degree that if we go
out in the backyard or out in the
football field and measure survey the
geometry of the football field uh we
could drive Stakes into the football
field stretch strings between the
stakes by stretching the strings between
the stes the stakes as tightly as
possible we construct straight lines we
can put uh several stakes in and create
triangles and measure the angles of the
triangles and what we find of course to
a very high Precision is that triangles
behave just like triangles and flat
space namely the sum of the angles add
it's up to
180° what do we learn from that we
learned that if the Earth is curved the
curvature is
small which is another way of saying
that if the Earth is a finite sphere
it's a big sphere much much bigger than
the field not the when I use the word
field now I'm not talking about
gravitational field I'm talking about
the field that we
surveyed uh it's precisely the same in
cosmology astronomers do a kind of
cosmic
surveying measuring
triangles thing in the sky over there a
thing in the sky over there that gives
you an angle
you may have some reason to believe that
you know the distances involved both to
the objects and also between the objects
assuming you have you do have some good
reason to believe those things you are
measuring the properties of
triangles and remarkably those
triangles of course I'm simplifying the
story a little bit what you really
measure is a little bit less direct than
that but uh that will be it effectively
comes to that we measure triangles and
we find the triangles behave like
ukian um flat triangles in ordinary
ukian space okay so apparently to a high
Precision space itself is flat but it's
expanding to make it expanding all we
have to do is put into this
equation
it's dt^ 2 just good old time
minus a scale factor a of t
squared it's squared because everything
in the equation is squared the units uh
let's as always will take the speed of
light to be equal to one and in that
case the units of time and the units of
space are the
same
uh
the units in this equation are the
squares of lengths and so if we take a
to be a
length
namely the distance between two
particular points as the points separate
and go apart then we should also think
of the X's as not having any Dimensions
there's two ways to think about it you
can either think that a has no
dimensions and the X's have dimensions
of
length uh the more conventional way to
think about it is the X's here have no
Dimensions they're simply labels of
points and when you say that the that
the distance between two points or the
separation between two points is Delta x
equals let's say 5 that's not a
statement about how far apart they are
that's just a statement of um well
here's the way to think about it again
think about the expanding rubber sheet
we draw coordinates in the expanding
rubber sheet and those coordinates
stretch and expand out with the
expansion so that going from x equal
let's put it over here zero to xal 1
over here corresponds to different
actual physical separations at different
times at an early time the actual
physical separation in meters between 0o
and one might be some tiny tiny distance
late late in the universe after the
universe has expanded many many times
the distance between 0 and one may be
very large that distance is
characterized by a of T so the actual
distance between points if Delta X were
five would be a * Delta X or 5 a and a
is a thing which since it varies with
time it must have some Dynamics there
must be some equations governing
it there must be some equations
governing how AF oft expands with
time
so that's our goal this
morning that's our goal this evening is
to work out some of the equations
governing
a
now I should tell you right now the
general theory of
relativity allows curved space when I
say space I don't mean space time I mean
space it allows space to be curved and
as long as it's homogeneous which means
the same everywhere there are three
kinds of
spaces which are
homogeneous any one of which could be
the right thing to write down
here as I said observationally we in
luck it looks like space just flat so we
don't have to write anything very
complicated the other two
possibilities are that space is round
like the surface of the Earth it's a
sphere but of course it's not a
two-dimensional sphere it's a
three-dimensional sphere a sphere
ordinary sphere incidentally let's get
something about
terminology when one talks about the
Earth the whole earth the body of the
Earth the bulk of the Earth the rocks in
the inside the mathematical term is a
ball a ball means the
solid
earth the term sphere refers to the
boundary refers to the surface of the
Earth so a sphere is a two-dimensional
surface okay
um
let's let's just talk about a little bit
what a sphere means first a circle
the circle you can just think of is the
locus of points x^2 +
y^2 equals some kind of radius
squared if R is one then it's a unit
circle so this the locus of points which
satisfy x^2 + y^2 = r 2 is just a circle
and a circle is a onedimensional
space and you and mathematicians would
call it a one sphere
a one sphere because it's onedimensional
what would you call the
interior two ball two ball or a disc
right the special case of two Dimensions
it has a special name of its own it's
called a disc but if we wanted to use
the generalized mathematical terminology
we would call it a ball two a
two-dimensional Ball but the boundary of
the ball is of course a circle and it's
a one sphere all right so if we add a z
s to this then we get a two sphere the
surface of the Earth or something like
that and it's pretty easy to
visualize I can see the surface of a
sphere in my head I cannot seem to free
myself of the third dimension I cannot
see the seem to see that sphere without
also seeing what's outside the sphere
and what's inside the
sphere but I know that
mathematically the surface of the sphere
without regard to what's inside or
outside is a mathematical space that can
stand by its own and does not have to be
embedded in three
dimensions the reason we have such a
damn hard time seeing two dimensional
spheres without the inside and the
outside is evolutionary we have been
built and constructed to recognize
three-dimensional space and we have not
been built and constructed to to be able
to see directly two dimensional space
without it being embedded in the third
dimension but then we come to something
even
worse we come this is a two sphere now
this
is uh the surface is a two sphere and
the interior is a three-dimensional
space the the the ball or the
three-dimensional
Ball but then it gets worse we can add
another coordinate
here now I can't even draw it for
you I can't draw it for you but I can
tell you that what is this this is the
locus of all
points which whose four-dimensional
distance from the origin is fixed at R
squ if I could draw it I would but I
can't because I have to be able to
picture four
dimensions just in order to be able to
see the three-dimensional sphere this is
a three-dimensional sphere just as when
I just had three
coordinates I was thinking about the
three directions in which you would
embed the two-dimensional sphere the
two-dimensional sphere is one lower
Dimension than the number of
coordinates if I add another
coordinate then I construct a three
sphere the interior of which is a
four-dimensional
ball but forget the interior for get the
exterior one possible kind of geometry
that we could live in
is the three-dimensional sphere the
three sphere now you can see from the
two
sphere that every point on the two
sphere is the same as every other point
of course the real Earth the North Pole
is different than the equator but uh
just as a geometry as a geometric
construction a
sphere is really quite homogeneous every
point is like every other point and so
homogeneity does not Force Space to be
flat it allows for example a
sphere moreover if you are at a point on
the sphere and you look in different
directions everything looks the
same and so a sphere is not only
homogeneous it's
isotropic a person on the sphere and we
could invent a cosmology in
fact uh it is was always the most
popular cosmology until experiment sort
of said well maybe it's not right which
was to
replace the flat plane here by the
sphere I won't write down the metric of
a sphere it's not important but just
think about the sphere as a space and If
I multiply it by a of T then as a grows
or shrinks it corresponds to a shrinking
or expanding
sphere okay it does not make
sense to
ask well if we think about the Big
Bang as a time when the sphere was very
small now remember we're not talking
about a two-dimensional sphere we're
talking about a three dimensional sphere
but nevertheless the best I can do in in
terms of drawing is to draw a
two-dimensional sphere if we start with
it very very
small then all the particles that were
in
it are squeezed together obviously
they're in no sense at a special place
on the sphere it's not that all the
particles were in some place and got
shot out of that place out into
space they were on
sphere the sphere was very small and so
the particles whatever they were whether
they're galaxies or electrons they were
all very very close together squished
into some very small space how
small we don't know how far we can trace
things back but we can probably Trace
things back to the point where the
observed
Universe was no bigger than a cranberry
or something so we can trace it back
along
ways and that's as far as we can go okay
with observation so we start with a
space which might be as big as a
cranberry filled with some large large
number of
particles and then started expanding the
particles spread out okay the further
apart they are the faster apart they
move because there are more pie more
little segments in between
so further apart in fact if they weren't
moving relative to each other faster
they couldn't have gotten further
apart so the further apart they are the
faster they
move
that's
closed
finite uh spherical universe that was
originally the most popular and our
universe may be like this it's
conceivable that it is like that but if
it is the sphere is so big
that like the Earth we can't uh see its
curvature by small scale
surveying and when I say small scale 10
billion light years is apparently a
small scale because we don't see any
curvature so we might as well then
replace the sphere by the flat plane the
three dimensional plane which is
three-dimensional space but the picture
is the same we have roughly the same we
have a plane with a lot of particles in
it if you like you can think of it as
part of a gigantic
sphere but it's being stretched
apart it's being spread
apart and as it spreads apart the points
which are embedded in it are also
spreading apart from each other and
they're spreading apart at a rate which
is proportional to the distance between
them that's the Hubble law
now we can take this
space and we can draw coordinates on
it the coordinates move as the space
expands when I say they move what I mean
to say is that as the space expands the
co coordinate separations between
neighboring points expand with it
coordinates like that which expand with
the expanding space are called
co-moving co-moving coordinates are
coordinates embedded in space which
expand with it in those coordinates
every Galaxy is at a fixed
place it's at a fixed
place because that that's of course an
approximation that's an approximation
it's an idealization but on a big enough
scale it's pretty much true if it's not
true of individual galaxies it is true
of
superclusters uh and as the universe
expands the location in the coordinate
mesh here of Any Given Galaxy stays
fixed but the separation between them
increases because of the scale factor
okay so if you like the scale factor
when you rule these coordinates and you
call this x = 0 and x = 1 then the scale
factor is just a physical distance
between x = 0 and x =
1 this distance between x = 1 and x = 2
is twice as big and so that's uh we can
write
that
as
distance distance between points is
equal to a * let's call it Delta
X now I showed you the last time but I
want to go through it again because uh
it is important the Hubble law deriving
the Hubble
law this is the physical distance
between two points and this Delta X
could be measured along any axis of
course but if I happen to measure it
along the x- axis let's let's do it
along the x axis this is Delta X
here and just for Simplicity let's let's
keep along the x-
axis um the galaxies don't
move in the coordinates
X that means if I time differentiate if
I take two
galaxies and Delta X is now the
separation between the two galaxies
Delta X does not change with time
supposing I want to time differentiate
this if I question if I time
differentiate it the left hand side
becomes comes the velocity between the
two galaxies so on the left that's the
time derivative of the distance on the
left we have the Velocity on the right
we have the time derivative of the scale
factor again time derivative being
represented by a DOT times Delta
X that's the
velocity now let me divide that and
multiply it
by
a why did I do that because I wanted to
get rid of Delta X by itself and replace
it by something more physically
measurable like a real distance so I
multiplied and divided by a in order
that Delta X here could be replaced by D
and what do I get I get that the
velocity is a do
a times the distance between
points now a do over a may depend on
time the scale factor depends on time so
does its time derivative but it doesn't
depend on where you
are so this equation which tells us
velocity in terms of distance and in
terms of a quantity which doesn't depend
on where you are is Hubble's Law
velocity is equal to Hubble constant
which isn't really a constant
time
distance but now we know what the
meaning of the Hubble constant is the
Hubble
constant is the
ratio a DOT over
a
so what we what we measure when we
measure the Hubble constant when we look
out measure the velocity of galaxies
divide it by the distance to a Galaxy we
always get the same number incidentally
if we look out at galaxies in that
direction at the at the 100 light years
or no we have we have to look out sorry
100 million light years we look at some
Galaxy out there we compute a Hubble
constant by dividing its velocity by its
distance we look at it another one in
that direction which is 600 million
light years away we divide the velocity
by the distance we get the same Hubble
constant
so excuse me
two different places two different times
yeah
yeah yes you're entirely right we have
to worry about that
but only if we look at exceedingly large
distances and the reason is the Hubble
constant itself a. over a varies on a
time scale of roughly the age of the
universe all right so that means if
we're looking out the distances which
are small by comparison with the age of
the
universe otherwise we have to take it
into
account to take it into account to take
the variation into account we have to
know how it varies how a and a DOT
varies for that reason we have to have
well not only for that reason but for
many reasons we would like to know the
equations which determine how a varies
with time okay so that's what we're
going to work out tonight
right oh there was one more geometry one
more mathematical yeah does the scale
factor affect the propagation that we
perceive light or gravity at a great
distance
M all
right so let's ask what are the rules
for light
propagation the rules for light
propagation is that along a light
Ray D to is equal to
zero let's just remember
why let's just draw good old special
relativity
again this is a light cone the
trajectory of a light Ray and along that
trajectory d X is equal to DT that's why
it's at
45° of course only when the speed of
light is set equal to one again always
the speed of light is one along here DX
is equal to minus
DT but along both branches DT ^2 is
equal to dx2 or DT ^2 minus dx^ 2 is
equal to
Z it's another way of saying that the
proper time along a light Ray is is
always
zero one way of thinking about a light
Ray is that it's a trajectory of zero
proper
time that rule extends into the general
theory of relativity D to is equal to
zero so let's see what it says imagine a
light Ray moving along x y and z are not
changing it's just moving along X we can
forget Y and Z what it says is that
DT is equal to a of t
*
DX what I've done is just
written I wanted to make this whole
thing zero so d y and DZ are equal to
zero by assumption light Ray going along
the x- axis and that means DT s must
equal a^2
dx2 for motion along the positive axis
that would just say DT is equal to a of
T *
DX now we could work out a kind of
velocity of
light not the ordinary velocity of light
but we could ask how large a distance
Delta X Now Delta X is not a true
distance remember it's just a
label okay but we could ask this light
Ray what is the amount of Delta X or DX
in a given time DT and that's easy we
just divide by DT and we find that DX by
DT
is not a constant but it's 1/ a of
T so in these coordinates light seems to
slow down as the universe
expands it's not really slowing down
it's just that a given DX corresponds to
a bigger and bigger distance as time
goes on so in order for light to have a
uniform
velocity since DX gets to be well since
distance true physical distance uh for a
given DX grows with
a this is just a
statement that the true ordinary
conventional velocity of light is
uniform but if expressed in terms of DX
and DT the light Ray seems to slow
down what the equivalent
then an equivalent uh
stma would be to hub's law would be that
light gets slower the further you look
away from us light goes
slower it's either that or the universe
is expanding or
equivalent you could probably find a
way to
um twist it into the statement that
light appears to go slower and slower as
you move further and further away but
you'd have to do some all kinds of funny
things to LAN and uh and it's probably
not the uh best way to think about it
but I'm sure you could is there any
evidence from the spectral lines from
the long distance that that at the small
levels light is going at regular speed
light
yeah well what do you mean by the
regular speed of light how could they be
what would what would an irregular speed
of light mean do would mean that light
isn't going as fast as light
well we know that on the whole the
Spectra from the galaxies is red
shifted is there any microscopic
evidence from Individual in galaxies
that
isn't red shifted there's a lot of
evidence that the dimensionless
constants of nature are the same
everywhere say it again always didn't
change yeah it always has been okay
what what would you mean by the
dimension of speed of light
[Music]
um let's try to think of some
uh of
some physical unit of
time my time x watch is not the one I
want to
use the time that it takes to an
electron in the inner orbit uh in the
first excited orbit to go around the
hydrogen
atom okay okay that's a that's a that's
a good unit of time let that be my unit
of time okay how about a unit of space
Oh well unit space could be the size of
an
atom I could ask what uh how long does
it take for
light or how many
Revolutions of the electron does it take
in order for light to cross uh to cross
the atom
okay that appears to be the same
everywhere as in the
universe okay the time that it would
take light to travel across an atom
where time is measured in some physical
unit we don't have to use we could use
some mixed units for example instead of
um instead of using the orbit of an
electron we could use some vibrational
frequency of a
nucleus take some particular nucleus and
look at something particular vibrational
frequency and the time for one
oscillation we could use that as a unit
of time and then we could ask how long
does it take in that unit of time for
light to cross an
atom okay that is some relationship
between scales in nuclei and scales in
atoms and it's a non-trivial fact that
that seems to be the same every place in
the universe now of course the argument
is indirect but that seems to be a good
good uh a good assumption that's what it
means to say that uh that the light
travels with the same speed
everywhere it's hard to imagine what it
would mean for light to not travel with
a speed of
light but uh when the universe the size
of
fan light actually would have been able
to Traverse across that very rapid
right take one light
cranberry no no one that's not quite
right a CR uh it's upside down
but could be a unit of time called a
light
cranberry
okay all right that's the basic setup
now as I said oh I didn't say there is
one other mathematical geometry that has
the property that it's the same
everywhere okay in two Dimensions it's
the negatively curved that the sphere is
a positively curved
geometry what does it mean to say it's
positively curved it's a statement about
triangles if you take a triangle on a
sphere it's pretty apparent that the
angles sort of bow out and so the sum of
the angles on a sphere is always greater
than 180° in fact you can make a
triangle with three with three 90° sides
to it three 90° angles very
easily so the sum of the angles is
always greater than
zero
um that's called a positively curved
space and it's true both in the
two-dimensional sphere and the
threedimensional sphere the
four-dimensional sphere if you make if
you make triangles the sums of the
angles are greater than zero all right
are greater than 180° and that's called
positive curvature there is also the the
negatively curved
geometry and it's harder to
draw it's a saddle surface I'm not going
to work out its mathematical properties
today but it can be it it stands on its
own terms as a geometry without having
to embed it in space but if I embed it
in space so that you can see it it would
look like a saddle
surface it may not look to you like
every point is the same as every other
point but the mathematics of the saddle
surface is such that it has uniform
curvature everywhere and it's negatively
curved the meaning of that is if you
draw triangles in it the triangles are
sort of pinched in and they have a sum
of angles less than
180° this is also uniform isotropic
homogeneous and either any of these
three geometries is a candidate for an
isotropic homogeneous cosmology as I
said experimentally or observationally
at least on the scales that we're
familiar with
it looks
flat okay now let's let's come to the
equations governing the expansion of the
universe we started it last time but
let's get back to
it let's call this point over here
us that's us
and let's draw a sphere around us it's a
big sphere so that it contains many many
many galaxies and clusters and
superclusters and so
forth and let's look at
some Galaxy over
here it's moving away from us we know
that let's write down well first of all
first fact first fact and this is a fact
really if space is flat even if it's not
not flat it's a it's close to being a
fact it's a fact of Newtonian
gravitational
Theory it follows from Newton's
gravitational law and from Newton's
equations it's a miracle it's what made
it possible for Newton to compute things
about about
gravity is that if you have a sphere
like this and if everything is
distributed spherically symmetrically in
other words if everything is isotropic
IC relative to the point
us there's as much mass here as here as
here as here as here so that everything
has nice spherical symmetry then it's a
theorem about it's theorem about the
inverse Square law that the
force on a particle over here the
Assumption now is that we're working
with coordinates in which we are at
rest we will we will just arbitrarily
use a coordinate system a frame of
reference where we are at rest and
velocities mean relative to US
accelerations mean relative to us
velocities accelerations motion now
means relative to us then it's a fact of
Newtonian physics that the only gravit
the only the net force on this point
here only comes from things inside the
sphere and things outside the sphere the
forces just
cancel uh um this is maybe well known to
you in
electrostatics that if you have a hollow
region and charge some charge
Distribution on the outside as long as
it's spherically symmetric then there's
no force on any particle on the inside
of that sphere it's only the charges on
the interior within which exert forces
net force on a particle so all of the
force on that particle comes from
masses in the interior
here okay that's one that's one
statement the next statement is that the
gravitational force of a spherically
symmetric distribution of matter is very
simple a very spherically symmetric
distribution of
matter on the
inside is very simple and it's just to
take the total matter on the inside
and think of it as being concentrated as
a at a point so the motion of this
galaxy relative to us is exactly the
same as if all of the mass as if you
ignore all the mass on the outside of
the
shell and take all the mass on the
inside of the shell and place it right
at that
point now that makes it very easy to
compute or at least to see what's going
on with this this particle with this
particle over here it behaves exactly as
a particle in a gravitational field
where all of the masses at the
center
and uh concentrated at the center this
is the key thing that made it possible
for Newton to do a lot of things with
gravity it's a thing which allows us
to uh to compute the properties of
cosmology okay let's put us at X
Z and let's call this point just X I'm
going to keep it on the x- AIS but of
course it doesn't have to be on the
x-axis first of all let's write down
some equations what is the distance out
to that point let's call it R now R
stands for radius but it actually means
physical distance let's say measured in
meters uh to uh to the point x well the
answer is it's x * the Hubble
constant no x * the scale
factor not the Hubble constant x times a
scale factor remember the relationship
between actual physical distances and
scale
factor is that you multiply the
coordinate Distance by the scale factor
to get the actual physical distance so
the actual distance to this object over
here
R is equal to x times the scale factor
and it's a scale factor which changes
with
time particle moves because the scale
factor moves away from us because the
scale factor changes with time what is
its velocity the velocity of the thing
moving away from us is x * a
DOT now let's remember now that we can
pretend we can pretend that this is an
equivalent
problem of a
projectile moving away from us under the
influence of gravitating mass point at
the
center what is the energy of that point
moving
away what would the energy be if all the
mass were concentrated at the center and
we could ignore all the mass on the
outside well there are two terms in the
energy potential and
kinetic the potential energy oh let's go
let's uh let's call the mass of this
particle over here little M the mass of
everything inside the shell we'll worry
about in a little while in fact we'll
call it Big M Big M is the mass of
everything inside the shell Little M is
the mass of the distant Galaxy that
we're
following all right what's the what's
the energy of that distant Galaxy it's
its kinetic energy 1/2 mv^
2 plus the gravitational potential
energy so the one new thing you have to
know is the potential energy of an
object in a gravitational field anybody
not know
it some people have seen r g r g M1 M2
over
R right product of the masses right so
then this potential energy what's the
sign negative negative because it's an
attraction so when a part when gets
pulled closer and closer and closer of
course it gets more energetic but the
energy goes down not up because things
tend to be pulled in direction of
decreasing energy so there's another
term and the other term is
minus Newton's
constant the product of the masses now
which Mass
the mass of the
projectile and the mass that's
concentrated at the center in our
imaginary uh in our imaginary
simplification that's all the mass
inside the sphere divided by
R that's the energy and here's what I
know I know that that energy is
constant it doesn't vary with
time that's what I I know that it
doesn't vary with time it could be
positive there's a positive kinetic
energy it could be negative if GM over R
is bigger than mv^ 2 1 12 mv^ squ then
the energy is negative whatever it is
though it is not allowed to change with
time
constant that would be the property of a
projectile moving away from us all right
I'm going to study the one special case
which corresponds to Zero Energy over
here later on I'll come back and tell
you what the connection between the
energy on the right hand side is and the
geometry of SpaceTime but just for
Simplicity let's take the total energy
gravitational plus kinetic to be zero do
it Mak sense to to to think that the
energy is zero yeah there a positive
term and a negative term you can make it
zero what do making it zero mean for a
projectile when you shoot it
up it means it's at the escape
Velocity okay it means it's EXA exactly
at the escape Velocity if the energy is
positive then it's beyond the escape
Velocity if it's negative it means it
falls back down okay so we'll come back
to
that three cases the energy could be
positive it could be zero it could be
negative I'm going to
take the simplest case the and then we
can come back and talk about the other
two cases the simplest case is that the
total energy is
zero it corresponds to things being shot
out at exactly the escape
Velocity it's the simplest
cosmology yeah Capal time oh no no no no
no no no no capital M does not vary with
time it's all the particles that are in
here but remember that they all move
together so as that sphere expands the
same number of particles that's an
extremely good point or extremely good
question uh it was a lousy statement it
was a very good
question uh the same number of particles
is always in that sphere so it doesn't
uh change with time but now let's write
it in terms of the density of matter in
the universe the density of matter in
the universe is the mass per unit volume
that does change with time as the
universe
evolves the material in the universe
gets thinner and thinner this means per
real volume real genuine volume measured
in cubic
meters so the amount of mass in a cubic
meter that cubic meter stays
fixed all right the cubic meter is just
a cubic meter the material moves out of
it and the mass and the and the density
does go down the total total mass stays
fixed the density
decreases the density decreases the
volume increases all right so this is
the this is the um mass per unit
volume what is
the total mass inside that shell the
total mass inside that shell is the
density row is a standard uh standard
notation for density is density time
volume volume what's the volume of a
sphere anybody
know 4/3 PK R Cub so
4/3 pi row R
cubed that's
M keeping in mind that
row is depends on time we'll we'll
discuss later how it depends on time
okay but basically it depends on time
just because the volume of the sphere
increases and the mass doesn't increase
so if the volume increases and the mass
doesn't increase row depends on time
that's the total mass in there so now we
can write down oh let's let's do this in
steps first of all this is the formula
for the mass inside the
ball in the
ball notice if I have zero on the right
hand side and this is one of the reasons
that I'm taking the case z zero on the
right hand side because it makes it a
little bit easier we can divide by the
mass of the
projectile so let's do that let's just
divide it out doesn't make any
difference it doesn't
matter if that is a Galaxy a star a
pebble we've just divided out its mass
it's gotten out of the equation
okay setting the difference of two
things to zero is the same thing as
setting them equal to each other so
let's just do it this
way and now let's plug in for the mass
let's plug in what we have here so I I
don't think I want to
uh
uh mess up that equation any further
let's let's leave it up there and work
on it down
here okay so let's just substitute
now the equation in the Box the capital
M that says that one
half the square of the
Velocity
okay of the outgoing projectile is G
over R and now let's put it it in 4 pi
over
row R
cubed use Newton's constant it came from
the right hand side of the energy
equation the r is also from the energy
and then the rest of this is just the
mass inside the shell of radius r
okay now let's use Hubble's Law Hubble's
Law says that the
velocity is equal to the Hubble constant
times the
distance
okay it can also be written in another
way and I'm going to do it this way I'm
going to write the velocity is equal to
a DOT over a a times the distance
because the Hubble constant is just the
ratio a DOT over
a okay let's plug that in and see what
we
get uh I guess I can continue to call it
the Hubble constant we
have2 the Hubble constant
squared times the distance
squared and the left hand side is
proportional to the distance to that
outgoing Galaxy squared why because of
of Hubble's
Law right now h of course depends on
time but we can use it in this equation
and that's equal to G well let's uh
let's take out the constants first
4/3
pi the density of matter oops 4/3 pi
G the density of matter 4/3 pi G density
of matter R cubed over r
that's r
s oh that's kind of nice we
have R 2 on both sides of the
equation that means we can cancel it
out that's kind of
interesting because what it tells us it
had to cancel out I'll tell you why
because the Hubble constant if we had
some if we have some way of calculating
it which we do now the Hubble constant
can't depend on how far away the Galaxy
that we're studying is it's supposed to
be the same for all the galaxies so it
better work out that the
equations if they're going to tell us
what the Hubble constant is in terms of
other things it had better not depend on
how far away the Galaxy that we're
studying is and it doesn't we could have
let we could
have that's us we could have used this
galaxy we could have used this galaxy we
could have used this galaxy they would
all give us the same
formula for the Hubble constant and what
does it say it says that the Hubble
constant is in some way not some way the
square of the Hubble constant let's
let's write it in a traditional way the
square of the Hubble constant is 8 pi
over three Newton's constant times the
density of matter in the universe times
the density of mass in the
universe
not on large enough scales the density
of material in the universe is
constant time it's a function of time
and so is the Hubble
constant yeah we could write that's
right we could write this another way
you could write it as a do over
a
squared is 8 Pi G over
3times row of
T you had to assume
that was the escape
Velocity
MH or evently that the energy was
Zero is there evidence that that's true
yeah I'm going to tell you what the
evidence is soon
well there one simple piece of evidence
we can measure the Hubble constant and
we can measure the density of matter in
the universe
I'm not going to tell you whether that
is same or
not that's cuz I haven't told you about
Dark Energy
yet let's but okay let's that's a b you
know
but when all forms of mass are accounted
for remember first of all you hear the
term Dark Energy all the time energy and
mass are the same thing
eal
mc^2 C is just a conversion factor from
energy to
mass so when I speak of mass I could
also be speaking of energy in units in
which the speed of light is one row can
be taken to be energy density energy
density mass density same thing and
there are variety of different kinds of
energy in the
universe different kinds of mass
different kinds of energy
there the masses of
stars there's Intergalactic
dust there's something called Dark
Matter and on top of everything else
there's vacuum energy when all of it is
added up the answer is yes these two
equations look like they balance to
about
1%
so uh
we could keep the other term that I
threw away which was just the constant
energy here we could keep it and I I
will tell you eventually what it
does what it
does
okay so yeah you
can first play the game of finding all
the energy in the universe everything we
know about putting it on the right hand
side measuring Hubble's
Constant and after many
decades and finding this kind of energy
and that kind of energy and so forth
this equation looks
good
okay so how much of however it does not
mean it does not mean that the universe
is at the escape Velocity because I have
made I we're going to make we're going
to make uh some I'm going to show you
some assumptions that came into that now
how does row depend on time that's the
big one how does row depend on
time
row we take some box in the
universe with a certain
volume it's the mass in that box let's
call it m divided by the
volume
okay there are various kinds of
situations let's take the first
situation the simplest situation that
the box is filled with
particles the particles aren't moving
very fast they're more or less at rest
they're what we call galaxies or what
else they're at rest relative to the
coordinates X
so we have a given
box
it's Delta X on this side Delta y on
this side and Delta Z in the other
direction and we're following the box as
it
expands it has a certain number of
particles in it and let's say that
number of particles stays fixed each
particle has a m mass and it's not and
they're not moving relative to uh to the
coordinates then what's the energy in
the in there the energy is just the
total mass which is the number of
particles which stays fixed divided by
the volume but what is the
volume the volume is the size of the
Box Delta X time a cubed
so whatever the size whatever is in that
box the density gets diluted by the fact
that a grows with time this is just the
statement that the Box gets bigger and
bigger a given amount of mass in a box
that gets bigger and bigger the density
will get smaller and smaller and it will
get smaller and smaller according to 1 /
a cubed so we can say that the density
of mass in the
universe is some constant divided by a
cubed
okay what is the constant here well
there's one simple way to specify the
constant the simple way to specify the
constant is to say what is the density
of mass
today on the left hand side I could put
the density of mass
today on the right hand side I could put
the scale factor
today
today now I can multiply it let's see
what do we want to do with it um all
right that's that's a correct equation
now how about at any time let's write
the same equation except at any time row
of
T is equal to C / a cubed of t
and let's divide these two equations
this one by this one that tells us that
row at any time
T divided by row
today it's this divided by this is the
ratio the the C's cancel out and it's
just the
ratio a cubed today
a / a cubed of
T row of T / row today is a cubed today
/ a cub of T and that's because Row in
each case is proportional to 1 / a
cubed okay so just dividing these two
equations and now we can write that at
any time the density of matter
the density
row is just whatever it is
today times the ratio of the scale
factor today and the scale factor at an
arbitrary
time
see the scale factor today is going to
drop out of all the equations but
basically the thing that it tells us is
that the density of material decreases
like 1 a cubed we can now try to put
that into here we have on the left hand
side something involving the time
derivative of a a itself and this
unknown row of T but now we know
something about row of
T we
know let's write it out again a DOT / a
sar is equal a 8 Pi G over 3 and now row
today which we
measure anybody know what the density of
material the density of mass in the
universe is
roughly like you have to guess how many
nut yeah yeah but that's that's
negligible nutrino
[Music]
density one atom per cubic
meter
no but that's not all of it
because it leaves out the dark M the
dark uh the dark matter and dark energy
and if you include it all it's about 50
atoms but it's of that order of
magnitude and it's something that in
principle we could in principle we could
measure it
directly in principle direct measure of
all the all the energy around
so what are we doing we have row today
we have a cubed
today ided by a cubed of
T now 8 Pi G3 row to a and even a cub
today are constants that is to say they
don't vary with time row row of course
row varies but row today is just row
today it's just a number that we measure
what about a today it is just whatever a
is today okay so it's just Frozen it
doesn't change with time the only things
which change in time are a a DOT and a
cubed over here so all together we have
an equation which looks something like
this a do over
a
squared is equal to some big constant
let's just call that constant C it
contains 8 Pi G3 row today a cub today a
all those things which don't change with
time divided by a
cubed this is a differential
equation that in principle will tell us
how a varies with
time I'm going to solve it for you well
let's just solve it let solve it it's
easy to
solve
[Music]
um the first thing let's get Let's uh
let's just multiply y on both sides by a
s to get the A squ out of the
denominator on both sides so let's do
that we have a do squ let's put it over
here a do
squar is equal to C I think it's just
divided by
a right I've Multiplied on both sides by
a
s we can um take the square
root square root of a constant is just
another
constant uh and what it says is that the
time derivative of a is proportional to
1/ theare root of
a let's
try rather than to solve it by doing
integrals and so forth let's just try to
solve it by saying a is
some power of the
time some power some some
coefficient some coefficient another
constant give me another name for a
constant
k k * t to the
P
okay what is a
DOT a DOT equal k p t to the P minus1
right and on the right hand side we have
the square root of this constant and now
we have 1 / the square otk of a which is
a to the minus
one2 there are two things that I don't
know I don't know the constant K and I
don't know the power T but now I look at
this equation
here and there's only sorry this is did
I make a mistake here not
um uh sorry Let's uh let's do this right
sorry mistake let's put down it is 8 -2
but 8 -2 is K to
-2 t- P /
2 A2 is K to the2 P to the uh sorry t to
the P
over2 right so I just plugged in for a
to-2 k to-2 and t Theus p over two for
this equation to make sense two things
have to match the powers of T have to
match that would just tell us that the
leftand side and the right hand side
vary the same way with time and the
coefficients have to be the
same that'll be enough to determine both
the power and the coefficient so let's
determine the power the power says that
P minus
1 equal Min - P
/2 I'm just equating P minus1 to minus P
/2 to make sure that the left hand side
and the right hand side vary the same
way with time okay so what does that
give that gives p is equal to one let's
let's get let's get all the P's over to
the left side so that's 3 p/2
is equal to 1 or P =
2/3 all right what does that tell us
that tells us that the Universe
expands like P to 2/3 t to the
2/3 T
2/3 is not as fast as just t t to the
2/3 increases more slowly than T itself
it's bigger than T square otk of T what
it is is just what it is a grows like T
2/3 so it just gets bigger and bigger
and
bigger uh in this manner here okay now
we know what p is p is 2/3 we can look
at the constants the con the
coefficients so that says let's put it
over here
KP and P is 2/3
2/3
K is
equal to the square root of C I've
forgotten what C is by now time K to the
12 and so now we have we can divide by K
to the2 we have K to the
12 and we
have K = C * 9 over
4 what was C anybody remember what C is
by this
time
yeah okay let's try to see what it
says let's come over to here and I I I
don't know what it says we're going to
find
out uh let's
uh let's see what it says okay so we
have k k = 94s
c k =
94s which is not so interesting but what
is C now I forgotten can somebody remind
me where is
it again start
over what is it 8
Pi G
over3 row to
a a cub today
what is this going to
say and now K * T to
2/3 T to
2/3 equals
a something's wrong with this
equation t to the 2/3 I don't know
what's wrong with it there's something
wrong with it uh
uh
um
oh uh no it looks
right it looks right but the main the
main thing here is we've determined How
the Universe expands it expands with a
scale factor that increases as the 2/3
power of time a to the
2/3 a = t to
2/3 with some known coefficient
um
I'm did I do something wrong was there
some
this I don't like the look of this
equation
um we should have the same power of a on
both sides of this
equation supposed to be a half
instead well you got it wrong okay how'
you do
that well let's let's do it a different
way let's do it a different way we had
that a
DOT a do over a was proportional to some
constant divided by a I think is that
right
H square root of a square root of
a so let's multiply by um let's multiply
by 8 to the 1/2 multiplying by 8 to the
1/2 here would give us a DOT all right
so that would give
us no no let's not do that
a a to the one2 what is
it I've lost track I've lost track um oh
oh here it is8 yeah yeah a do over a
s a do over a 2 so we multi we first
multiplied by a squ to get rid of the a
squares in the denominator that gave us
a do
2 that's what I meant to write down is C
over a now I think I have it
right all right and this is Da and da by
DT
squared let's multiply it by
a and now take the square root of both
sides square root of both sides gives a
square root of a d a
DT equals a constant right square root
of a constant is just another
constant now let's multiply by
DT and integrate what's the integral of
constant time
DT constant time t c ter
T
constant what's the integral of a to
the2 a to the
3es so a to the 3es is proportional to T
and T is prop and a is proportional to T
to the
2/3 okay so 2/3 is right so this is an
example
of uh
how nothing more than Newton equations
is enough to tell you uh the expansion
properties of the
universe and it just continues to
expand what it's interesting to ask what
happens to the Hubble
constant what will happen to the Hubble
constant with
time we know that
a is some constant different all of
these constants are different but we
know that it's a constant time T 23
what about a DOT a DOT is 2 over 3 C * t
to the uh 2/3 to the minus
1/3 just differentiating t to the 2/3
you get T Theus 1/3 or 2/3 * T Theus 1/3
now take a do over a that's the Hubble
constant the Hubble constant is a do
over a so that's 2/3
C tus
13 ided c t
23 C's cancel and you find that the
Hubble constant is
2/3 over
T that tells us how the Hubble constant
will change with time all right so this
answers the
question at least for with the
assumptions that we've made
this answers the question of how the
Hubble constant varies with
time if this is the way things really
work and we do look back into the past
then we should account for the fact that
the Hubble constant
increases like one overt all right so
this would give us we now have a
detailed prediction for what we should
see very far away we should see things
moving away from us with a Hubble law
but but the Hubble Law changes with time
so the further away we are the bigger
the Hubble constant should look to us
according to this formula and that's
that's a pretty good uh that's a pretty
good representation of what actually
happens to go beyond
this we have to know something about the
general theory of
relativity and that's beyond the level
of what we're doing so I'm going to tell
you a fact
we discussed the fact that there are
three
geometries that can describe homogeneous
isotropic
universes we can call them positively
curved zeroc curved that's this case
that we've been doing and negatively
curved there are also three possible
values for the total energy positive
zero and
negative these go together the three
possible values of the energy or the
three possible signs for the energy plus
zero and minus are in one to one
correspondence and this only follows
from Einstein's equations this you
cannot derive just using
Newton positive total
energy first of all means that the
universe is beyond the escape Velocity
and it will continue to escape it will
continue to go
out positive total
energy means negative
curvature so such a cosmology would not
only be Eternal into the
future but it would also be eternally
infinite in space Okay negative curved
space goes on and on forever but it
wouldn't be flat space it would be
negatively curved space
all right zero total energy that's the
case we
did that
corresponds the zero curvature
flat and negative
energy that corresponds to positive
curved Universe like a
sphere but positive energy sorry sorry
this is negative energy negative energy
or also means that you're below the
escape
Velocity negative energy means you're
below the escape Velocity the
implication of that is that the universe
will go out and expand and then turn
around and recollapse all we have to do
is focus on that one particle out there
that we that we were
studying
one Galaxy that we focused
on all that mass in there
if the velocity is above the escape
Velocity escape velocity for all the
mass that's in here concentrated at a
point if the escape Velocity if we're
above the escape Velocity that means the
energy is positive and it means the
universe will continue to expand forever
if we're below the escape Velocity and
that's the case where the total energy
is negative then every single Galaxy
will turn around and fall back in
at least according to the assumptions we
made
now there's a number of things
wrong with what we did the most
important is that we have assumed
um a model for the energy density and
the way it varies with time we said in a
given volume there's a fixed amount of
mass and that mass will
simply stay the same as the volume
increases and that was the origin of the
statement that the uh that the density
do we have it here that the density goes
like 1 over a cubed the volume
increases the amount of mass inside
stays the
same is that
necessary well there are lots of
examples where that's not true let's
take the following case supposing
instead of galaxies or or bowling
balls or even protons or neutrons
supposing what's in this
box is
photons photons of all different kinds
of
wavelengths okay mass is energy so what
we're interested in is the amount of
energy in this box as it
expands what's the connection between
the energy of a photon and its
wavelength first of all
eal H new so the energy of each
individual
photon is H * its frequency uh we can
write that in terms of the
wavelength frequency over
wavelength frequency over wavelength so
the bigger the
wavelength the smaller the energy of a
photon now what happens to if we have a
box and we expand the Box
what happens to a photon of a given
wavelength well the answer is it just
stretches out to match the box so the
wavelength of the photon will get bigger
as the Box increases the number of
photons in the Box will stay the
same uh the average number of photons in
a box will stay the same if the Box gets
bigger then the wavelength will get
bigger and the energy will
decrease so we have a box then
not with a bunch of particles with fixed
energy but a bunch of particles whose
individual energies are
decreasing what why does the wavel Fig
stretches with the box it's the same
phenomenon that happens if you have a
guitar
string and there's your guitar string
between two
posts
you put your finger down over
here so that the effective guitar
string is only this
long you pluck
it and then you move your
finger what happens you hear the tone go
from the tone associated with this
length of string through a tone
associated with this L length of string
what
happens is that uh at the wave you
started with just gets stretched
out so
uh you can test this theory if you own a
guitar if you play the guitar you'll
know this very
well so the um if the container that a
bunch of photons are in increases in
size then the uh then the energy of each
Photon Goes Down And if the energy of
each Photon goes down that means the
energy density in
there decreases even faster than it
would if each Photon stayed with the
same amount of energy if it stayed with
the same amount of energy that's the
situation where the
density is C over a cubed what happens
with a box of photons is it goes as C
over a to the 4th power it decreases
more rapidly as the uh as the B that's
easy to derive you just say that each
Photon instead of having a fixed energy
has an energy that goes like one over a
as the universe expands and so you get
the same formula except an extra power
of a in the denominator you go right
back to over
here and instead of saying that row goes
like 1/ a cubed you say that row goes
like 1 over A8 to the 4th and redo the
entire
analysis and then you get a different
answer you don't get 8 to the
2/3 you
get a to
the2 in other words the universe expands
a little more
slowly a little more slowly than it
would 8 to the 2/3 expands a little
faster than 8 to the
2/3 is that right yeah
sorry t to the 2/3 t to the 1/2 is a
little slower than t to the
uh yeah that's
right now there's
a okay so the
answer depends on the nature of the
energy very very early in the
universe the universe was filled with
hot photons most of the energy was in
the form of photons notice uh if it's of
course if it's true that as you expand
the Box the energy of each Photon
decreases it's also true that if you
squeeze the Box the energy of each
Photon increases if you take a box with
a bunch of photons low energy photons
very low energy photons let's say and a
bunch of
protons then the protons and neutrons
and electrons and so forth
atoms then the
atoms will ordinarily be most of the
mass in there but then you start
squeezing the Box the atoms each atom
stays the same mass but each Photon you
increase the energy of it so eventually
when you squeeze it
enough the photons will become the
dominant form of energy in the universe
this is going back in time squeezing the
universe means going back in time
sometimes time in the
past when the universe was about a
thousand times smaller in radius than it
is now when the scale factor was about a
thousand times smaller the dominant form
of energy was
not particles ordinary particles but
photons at that time the universe was
expanding like T to the
1/2 not t to the 3 haves incidentally by
now we have good evidence for this have
good evidence for essentially all of
this so before the
time as a time there a crossover time
when the universe became dominated by
ordinary matter and before that it was
dominated by
radiation okay so this is called the
radiation dominated Universe t to the
2/3 is called the matter dominated
Universe there's one other
example which is extremely
important and it's the energy of the
vacuum now I'm not going to tell you
much about the energy of the vacuum I'm
going to tell you only one thing about
it the thing which is true of vacuum
energy and there is vacuum energy in
Quantum field Theory it's a component of
the energy which does not dilute when
you expand the universe whatever the
vacuum energy is it's a property of
empty space and no matter how big the
universe gets the vacuum energy density
stays the same for our purposes that
defines vacuum energy a component of the
energy that just doesn't go down as the
universe
expands let's just see what it would
do supposing there was a component of
the
energy which just didn't refuse to
decrease let's just call it constant
it's the vacuum energy in fact it's
about 70% of all of the energy in the
universe so it really is the dominant
thing today it doesn't go down it's also
true that as you go backward in time it
doesn't go up if you take all the other
forms of energy and you squeeze it into
a smaller volume the energy goes up so
in the past the vacuum energy was not so
important in the future as all the other
terms in the energy get smaller and
smaller smaller and smaller 1 a cubed 1
A4 the vacuum energy will become the
most important component it's already
the most important component by a factor
of uh two more 70% is is vacuum energy
let's solve this equation what does it
say it says da by
DT 1/ a I'm taking the square root of it
is the square root of 8 piun G over 3
that's a
constant
times row to the 12 that's also a
constant everything on the right hand
side is a
constant I'll multiply equation by
a this
says that the time derivative of a is
proportional to a constant time a what's
the solution of
that exponential
the time derivative is a constant times
the thing
itself
okay the solution of
this is
exponential of square root of all this
stuff time
T all the stuff being the stuff in
here so this is an exponentially
expanding Universe a universe which is
dominated by vacuum energy expands
exponentially uh how long does it take
for it to
double well it looks like with the
present value of the vacuum energy it
takes about 10 billion years for it to
double so it looks like we're heading
off into a world where the universe will
simply be doubling roughly every 10 or
12 billion
years uh why that's true we don't know
but it's an empirical fact it appears it
appears to be an empirical fact that
there's a component of the vacuum energy
which is constant which doesn't dilute
as you expand and which causes the
universe to exponentially
increase
um and in
fact when we look out into the universe
it does appear to be exponentially
increasing if you look far enough away
very very large distances it looks like
the universe is exponentially
expanding so
that's I've told
you a small fraction of everything there
is to know about cosmology but I've told
you really the main uh tools and the
main uh the main facts about
it
um any questions yeah first vacuum
energy in some sense corresponds to Dark
Energy but they're not the same thing
yeah same thing same same thing
absolutely um second thing is we defined
the co moving
coordinates how do the photons know that
we be find the coordinates to be
increasing decrease their energy
yeah
um I think I think the best way to think
about it is in terms of this rubber
sheet picture uh space is like a rubber
sheet in general
relativity and um it the photons of
course don't know that we defined
anything at all okay but they can tell
that a region of space has doubled in
size they can tell that one wavelength
or one a region of size one wavelength
in a certain amount of time may have
doubled in size or done whatever it does
that's really all they can tell they can
tell the stretching of space g well they
don't even know anything about the
galaxies they know that space is
separating but yeah I mean you can you
can uh
uh remember that those photons another
way to think about it is through the
Doppler
shift
um let's
see
if
yeah
where good where did the photons come
from in the universe they came yeah
let's
uh okay
let's draw a picture of the universe
from our own
perspective we're sitting at the center
and we're looking out around us and we
see shells of different uh radius let's
say there's the solar system is like
that there's the Galaxy that surrounds
us which is like that there distances
out to the coma super cluster which is
out there and if we go out far
enough we come to a place called the
surface of L
scattering now as you look deeper and
deeper into the universe the material
was more and more
squeezed and because it was squeezed it
was
hotter so as you look out you not only
see earlier times but as you look far
enough out the material out here was
dense enough and hot enough that it was
opaque it was as opaque as the sun
somewhere as out here it was as hot as
the
sun and you simply can't see through the
sun the sun is opaque it's opaque
because it's full of unmatched electrons
and protons free electrons it's a plasma
light can't move through a plasma well
far enough into the early early um
Universe the universe was a plasma but
when we look back we look back in time
and eventually we see back to the time
when it was a plasma that's called the
surface of last scattering when we look
back so there's some sphere around us
that's um that's looks as hot as the Sun
but it's also moving away from us with
almost the speed of
light why because of Hubble's
Law so today that today if we were to
plug in the numbers or we were just to
look back and use the uh use what we
know here we would discover that that
surface of last
scattering is moving away from us or was
moving away from us of course we're
looking back in time but it's receding
away from us with almost the speed of
light that
means that a photon that comes from
there is doler shifted and it's Doppler
shifted a lot it's Doppler shifted a lot
because this surface is moving away very
very rapidly okay now what about and
once you know that it's Doppler shifted
you know something about the
wavelengths the wavelengths of the
radiation that are coming from this hot
surface are about the same as the
wavelengths of the light coming from the
Sun they Doppler shifted and when they
Doppler shifted they're elongated and we
see them being a thou roughly a thousand
times longer wavelength than the photons
of the sun and a thousand times less
energetic okay so we see long wavelength
photons here because they've been
Doppler shifted now let's go back into
the past and ask what the same picture
would have looked like much much earlier
much much earlier the surface of last
scattering would have been closer into
us if we could go back in time and ask
our ancient
ancestors uh four or five billion years
ago what did the universe look like they
would say the same picture except that
they would say the surface of last
scattering was closer and moving more
slowly moving more
slowly so they would see less of a red
shift less of a red shift right they
would see less Doppler shift because
they would see the surface of less
scattering moving away from them somewh
more
slowly right in fact if you go Way Way
Back the surface of last scattering was
very near and hardly moving at
all hardly moving at all and as time
went on it receded and sped up and sped
up and sped up okay so the photons if we
went back in
time several billion years the photons
that we see coming from the surface of
last scattering would have been shorter
wavelength so as time goes on the photon
that we see that make up the microwave
background for example uh as time goes
on the photons that we actually see
right here have longer and longer
wavelength because they originated from
a place which was moving progressively
faster and faster away from us so that's
another way to think about it both ways
are correct you can either think that
the Universe was expanding and each wave
got stretched out and so that's why we
see longer wavelengths with time or you
can imagine that the same kind of waves
were emitted from the surface of last
scattering but by the time they reach us
they've been more red shifted the
later we get to look at them yeah here's
what I don't understand about this uh
it's the conservation of energy thing
you have a photon of H new it's
emitted all right the time it arrives at
us it's red shifted lot M and it has now
less energy MH what what has happened to
the energy of that phon okay so let's go
back the basic
equation that we wrote for
cosmology was nothing but energy
conservation it with this equation you
can't violate energy conservation but
you have to remember there are two kinds
of
energies uh by the time we go through it
this term over here has morphed into a
do over
a^2 the expansion of the universe the
other term over here is just the energy
density of the
universe this is energy conservation and
it says there's two kinds of energy in
the world one is the energy of expansion
it's a kind of kinetic energy of
expansion and the other is just the
usual things that we call
Energy neither one by themselves is
conserved it's just they're just not
conserved they're not conserved so I'll
I'll explain it in another way in a
moment but they're not conserved by
themselves only the combination of them
is conserved and that's the equations we
used so in time as the
energy let's say in photons goes
down the total energy in photons goes
down it gets transferred into a um into
the kinetic energy of expansion
yes yes the well you can think of it as
a kind of pressure
um
the what happens to energy conservation
supposing you really did have a
box and let's imagine this is a box with
movable
walls the walls can
expand let's let's even make it more
realistic it's not a box it's a cylinder
with a pist
piston
okay there's the piston piston can go in
it can go out and we have a lot of
photons in
here what happens to that box that box
expands because of the pressure of the
photons on the Piston okay what happens
to each Photon each Photon decreases its
energy because its wavelength gets
longer where does that energy go it goes
into the kinetic energy of the
Piston
okay that's where it goes goes into the
K or it might go into friction but let's
uh you know let's idealize it no
friction it goes into the kinetic energy
of the Piston that's what's going on
here the um the energy the decrease of
the energy of the photons is being
transferred to kinetic energy of
expansion so it's a very similar thing
to
this uh
and energy is funny in the general
theory of
relativity it's conserved but it's also
exactly
zero uh in this case here we just
manifestly made it exactly zero uh the
rules for energy in the general theory
of
relativity are
peculiar either you take into account
all all energies that are around
including the energy of
expansion in which case it's conserved
but
zero or you forget this expanding energy
and Just Energy isn't conserved it just
isn't
conserved uh in the general theory of
relativity any any row that you put in
there whatever the tide dependence of
row is it's going to drive the a to have
some cor time so this is what you're
saying you just you're putting a row in
there that has some behavior in
yep so well even if row even if row even
if row is constant with time because the
ex the universe people always ask where
does all the energy come from if you
have vacuum energy in the universe
expands if you have a constant energy
density and the universe expands rapidly
it sounds like the energy of the vacuum
is increasing and that component is
increasing where is it going it's going
into the expansion here and it drives
the expansion even more rapid ly than uh
than the other forms of energy so in
thinking about energy conservation in
general relativity you must worry about
this term and this term is very
important it's the expansion of the
universe and it's simply cancels changes
in this cancel against changes in
that uh yeah in the first expression for
the metric that we started from yeah the
scale factor what was the reasoning that
the scale factor Vector multiplies the
space part but not the time part oh we
could have had it multiply the time part
would make no difference let me show you
why
um
yeah that's
definition okay let's uh let's suppose
it also multiplied the time
part so we have a of t
time let's just write simply dt^ 2 minus
dx2
okay all right does this is a
squared all right this is just a
redefinition of what we call time let's
invent a new
quantity new time which is such that
DT a new time which is equal to a of t d
T we can integrate both sides of this
equation and we can find out what Big T
is in terms of little
T then a^ 2 * little dt^ 2 is the same
as just big dt^
2 so you can always get rid of an a of
t^2 in front of a dt^ 2 by a change of
definition of time that's done but that
won't get rid of it multiplying to the X
squ so we'll still have
minus a of little T but we can also
think of it as in terms of Big T
dx2 so the issue of whether a of T
multiplies dt^ s is a question of
definition um mathematically there's no
difference
between um the two forms although you do
have to change the definition of time to
go back and forth between them
so uh yeah
if the universe was curved would we
expect to see galaxies coming towards us
at a high
velocity
uh that depends on whether that depends
on the magnitude of the vacuum energy
let's Suppose there was no vacuum energy
okay if the universe were positively
curved the question is analogous to the
following question supposing we shoot a
rocket out with less energy less
velocity than the escape Velocity and we
look at it through a telescope do we see
it moving out or do we see it moving
in well I don't know I mean it could be
moving out or it could be moving in the
one thing we know for sure is if we wait
long enough it'll be coming in we could
have caught it while it was going
out uh but uh but and we catch the
universe as it's expanding there's no
doubt of that the issue is not whether
it's expanding now or not the what we
see when we look out the the issue is if
we wait long enough into the future will
everything turn around and crash back on
top of
us and if there was no vacuum energy if
there were no vacuum energy then the
answer would be if the universe were
positively curved it would collapse back
on
itself uh the vacuum energy if it's
large enough will prevent that and it
certainly does look large enough so it
looks like our future independently of
whether we're curved or whether we're
positively curved negatively curved or
flat it looks like our future is one in
which the universe will simply
exponentially expand now that's not such
a good thing either if it
exponentially it's not it's not a good
future in any case well if it
exponentially
expands eventually all the stars will
burn out uh everything will cool down
everything will dilute all ordinary
forms of energy will exponentially
dilute because if the universe is
exponentially expanding its volume is
exponentially expanding all the energy
densities of all the other kinds other
than the vacuum energy density will also
exponentially dilute and will just be in
a universe with nothing in it or with a
thinner and thinner energy density so uh
there is no good end to the
story also um a great distance away from
us would there be an increased amount of
photons
because um in the early Universe was
dominated by
photons and the universe
expands um since the photons move faster
than say the mass the matter that was in
there could you
expect as you look back into the past
the ratio of photons to
ordinary
particles
um well let's see how to say it I I
would say more than saying that the
number of
photons doesn't get larger than the
number of um it's already true in our
universe that the number of photons is
much much larger than the number of
atoms 10 the 10th times
larger so we are dominated by photons I
don't mean the photons from light bulbs
I don't mean the photons from the Sun I
don't mean the photons from Stars I mean
the microwave background from The Big
Bang we are certainly dominated by uh by
photons now as you go back in time the
ratio of photons to protons stays about
the same okay but the photons get more
and more energetic and the protons
don't so as far as energy goes as you go
back into the past the energy will be
Domin dominated by the
photons the number of photons will stay
the same but their energy will increase
as you go back into the past the number
protons will stay the same but uh but
their energy won't increase or at least
not as
fast good okay I'm tired Let's uh let's
go
home and this is the last class
[Applause]
[Music]
the proceeding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu